[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
sorry i was saying welcome back welcome
back dave thanks for coming back
um welcome back to part three of
naturalizing sense making with
sensemaker in residence dave snowden uh
last session dave spoke about his
evolving kidnapping framework for
orienting action
in organizational space and i believe
this session he'll be discussing his
adaptation of
apex predator theory i'm right um
as usual first dave is going to present
some content that he prepared
uh during which time i encourage you to
post your questions
in the chat um this will be recorded and
posted to youtube so
um if you would like me to ask your
question on your behalf just indicate so
with your
question and uh without further ado i
would like to pass it over to dave
okay so um first of all apologies for
last week happened to be cancelled
everything got a bit difficult at the
last minute
and i'm now in a cottage in the middle
of the lake district um
on a walk-in holiday so um yeah i'm
hoping the internet
will stand up it's been okay so far um
but i have to change to the iphone on 3g
so but it looks okay um
what i want to do is to go through apex
predator theory i'm not sure this is the
right name for it i coined it some time
ago
um because my initial focus was
literally on the apex
um and i'll define that in a minute
but i'm now getting much more interested
as well in things like
keystone species and other aspects of
trophic cascades so
this is a framework looking for a name
at the moment
it may stay as apex but it tends to
focus people on dominating in the space
rather than for example enabling the
space so
i'll run through that if i get a chance
i'm going to introduce
the concept of rich data as well to go
with big data and thick data
because i'd like to leave you to
something to think about before we come
into that next week which is the fourth
week in the final week
so this stuff actually goes back before
kidnapping
um it's when i was working in corporate
and one of the key books i read at that
time
um was the book called crossing the
chasm
um which i still recommend and i don't
recommend many popular management books
i generally think they're a load of
bloody rubbish but
this one kind of like worked partly
because he made some predictions which
came true which is always
impressive most management books are
heavily retrospective
um and what what he did was to take the
basic
concept of a life cycle and that's
normally drawn as like
a big curve and within that cave
you have different groups you have early
adopters you have the majority late
majority lag guards and so on
um now that's been around for a long
time it goes back to procter and gamble
and there are well established
statistics
and there's some broad principles um if
you move into the early majority phase
and
you can command total market share if
the dominant market player at the end of
that you control the latter stages of
the life cycle of a product and so on so
there was a body of theory he built on
but what he critically said is that
there is actually this thing called the
chasm
so you get these and there's various
names on this and i'm still playing with
them but you get people who
you know the guys who always buy
something new doesn't matter what it is
they've got to have the new thing
uh they're the ones that queue up
outside the apple store rather than wait
24 hours you know and get some sleep
um and these people are vital to the
launch of new products
and the key thing to understand about
this group
is that they want to know how it does it
they're not so interested in what it
does
and this is a critical distinction so
they're they're guys who want the latest
car because they don't believe cars are
to drive around they think cars have to
take apart
and put back together on the weekend
they like to get involved
and dirty um and
that's normally well you say something
new these guys want something they're
prepared to accept failure in fact
they quite like failure because then
they can get involved in helping you fix
it
um and most products start there
and if they succeed then people draw
projection growth
yeah on the traditional life cycle curve
and assume it will carry on
carry on going what more established is
that actually that isn't the case you
get this sudden drop
so everything is going fine then all of
a sudden you don't get any sales for a
bit
and that's the chasm between these early
enthusiasts
and the early majority and the key
behavioral difference
is the first group are buying uh
what it does and the second group are
buying
sorry the first group of buying how it
does it and the second group
by what it will do for me now critically
they don't want to know what it will do
for other people because they want first
mover advantage this is why this is a
key phase
so the early group that is about two and
a half percent of the total markets and
i'll class them as early
adopters for the moment because that's
the phrase i used it's not
strictly what moore does but the early
adopters
they they love novelty they love new
things i remember when we were building
new software
based on stock forecast forecasting and
industry management algorithms working
with cranfield university
doing something which actually i'm
bringing back in now because everybody's
forgotten about variable buffer stock
as a way of handling uncertainty and you
can do that in crisis management as well
comes from the study of the operational
research background
so we were introducing new software on
that and we got the classic early
adopters so we got coca-cola
um we got british aerospace we got nato
if you're selling to early adopters
there's no industry specialization at
all
these are the people in their industry
who like to do things new and they can
afford to waste some money because they
like to grab them first
and i still remember we did a big
seminar out at
namsa which is the supply division of
nato
and the bastards were actually making
deliberate mistakes in algorithms to see
if we spotted them when they were
discussing what we did on the board
and then they told us how we could have
done it much better if only only we'd
listen to them this is the other
characteristic of early adopters if you
want to sell to them
they can always tell you how they would
have done it better the fact nobody is
prepared to fund them they can like
conveniently forget
i should say the whole of the software
industry is a bit like this show any
software to any software programmer and
they'll tell you you chose the wrong
language
rather than actually thinking about it
so these are a right bloody pain to be
honest and when you hit the chasm and
everybody's expecting ongoing
sales um the early adopter the the early
majority phase on the
home which is about 13 and a half
percent of the total market
these guys aren't concerned about how it
does it they want to know that you've
done it
they're not going to do it for the first
time but then they want to know what it
will do for them and what the risk is
yeah they want first mover advantage
they don't want to be second movers but
they don't want to be bleeding edge to
use the sort of convention
and an awful lot of companies never make
the switch
you know they start off and startup
companies are hugely enthusiastic about
how they do things and their wonderful
algorithms and their brilliant ideas
they just want to keep telling you that
it's kind of you know the future stuff
um and they don't realize when the
market switches to benefits and that's
another driver
yeah on the castle either the sales
behavior doesn't work
so we did a big piece of work on that it
was part of the genus program
in data sciences which turned us around
from a penny a share to about
i think 40 pounds a share in 18 months
when ibm bought us
um and it was basically we sat down one
day
um and i remember sitting there with the
white board and saying guys we can't go
through
this we've got to get new products to
market
and we can't go through this phase so
we've got to cross the chasm we've got
to jump across the chasm
and that's what i started to specialize
in and that was what got me
one of the things which got me into the
strategy roles in iobm and elsewhere was
that basic concept
and the way we did at that time is we
were world leading experts on something
nobody wanted to buy
which is you know kind of like immensely
self-satisfying but
not good for the business yeah so we
were experts in what was called
then radinjad it had been invented by
ibm rapid application development joint
application design
invented by am in canada forgotten um
we were picking it up and using it a lot
it was kind of like early stage agile
this comes way before agile
although it's one of the feeders so we
were really good at that but the trouble
is it was entirely novel and nobody want
to buy it
yeah the other thing we were really good
at was object orientated programming and
object libraries in fact we were
pioneering the use of object libraries
to get reuse code the way to do that by
the way is not allow programmers access
to source code if they ever see source
code they want to reinvent it
yeah you have to force them through some
of the gate on that but either way we're
building experts in these things we did
defense
contracts which would be magnificent the
trouble is we couldn't get to commercial
markets now
what i then did was to say okay so
what's the big thing everybody's got
budgets for at the moment
where there's no question they've got to
buy and effectively you've got a
seller's market
if you've got a seller's market you can
get away with damn more than the buyers
market
and at that time it was like legacy
system management you may remember this
is in the build-up to the year 2000
and i still remembering remember
removing cobalt and fortran for my cv in
1995 because they didn't want anybody to
know i could code in that because i knew
what would happen
yeah in a few years time um
so everybody is buying legacy system
management we had no history in that
but the market leader in europe was a
company called unilog
um so i got in touch we had some
meetings
we had a slight bond there and the
director responsible was for breton
yeah and if you don't know it bretton is
the same as welsh
so we could chatting welsh and nobody
neither of our two boys knew what the
hell we were doing
and if you know anything about companies
in france you'll know that for a brat on
to become a director of a
company otherwise run by grundy coles
from paris it's kind of like this guy
was bright
right so they were market leaders in
europe so we basically
took their method on intact as european
distributors so we had lay method
francais which
always goes down within with
english-speaking audiences as well
um and what we did is we differentiated
it with radja
object orientation so we said we can
object encapsulate your legacy code so
you can reuse it in modern software
and we've got rad jab techniques which
means we can rapidly work
out what you really need to do and get
you better focused
and that was maybe two percent of a bid
i don't think we ever did
object encapsulation by the way but
everybody thought it was a cute idea
and what it meant is they bought us
because
we could do the conventional stuff and
we had credibility that's a late
majority
market yeah they were buying our
reference sites all of which were france
or germany with pluncher as well
but we had this interesting little thing
which it departments got mildly excited
about so they kind of like preferred to
have
us than one of the big consultancy firms
because they could get exactly what the
big consultancy firm was doing with
these extra things as well
and within about a year those were
dominating our sales because as they
started to use rather
they suddenly realized the effectiveness
of it so they commissioned us to do more
and that was a turnaround of the company
and that is called a symbiotic marketing
strategy
you know and kind of like it's something
i'm paranoid about you should never
try and sell on the left hand side of
the chasm
yeah the secret to success is to bring
something in on the right hand side and
one thing i'm going to talk about next
week
is how do you repurpose existing
capability to match
unarticulated needs um
because that's where you really gain
advantage and there's a whole science
behind how you do that
it comes from the weak signal detection
what we did in darpa
so that was kind of like successful that
got me into market life cycle
and then as i moved into ibm research
and then left ibm research and
set up data cognitive edge this stuff
started to come in because we were
introducing sensemaker which at that
time
was a complete unique nobody had ever
thought of a quantitative approach to
narrative before
let alone an approach based on epidemic
justice principles
namely allowing people to interpret
their own narratives
um so we started to look at that
and then i started to see a broader
pattern in this
and complexity theory was coming in with
its emphasis on context and so what i
did was i took moore's concept of
crossing mechanism
and i also took s-curves which i first
came across in charles handy
but actually predate that in economics
and what i did was to combine the
two now at this point i'm going to share
a screen
i think i finished with a cat last time
but that is definitely a predator
um so what i did was to combine the two
so i took an s curve and took it down a
bit and i took the market life cycle
curve and introduced the chasm
all right so hopefully you can see that
it's kind of like you know the nescaf
like that there's this bigger
sort of market life cycle with a drop in
the middle
so basically something takes off it's
completely novel
then it goes into the chasm then it
becomes dominant
and then it moves on so this is a
combination of s
curves and life cycle theory per
more so that's cool but the big
realization i had was that actually
the previous cycle is one of the reasons
for the chasm
so let me run through this with my
favorite example
so one of the reasons that the
completely novel idea
is ready for penetration people are
prepared to buy it
is because the old idea or the old
product is starting to
run out of utility or is becoming a
commodity
so that creates a space for something
new
because it's at the end of the life
cycle you know the buyers are
conservative
buyers so nobody wants to buy the new
stuff
and that's the reason you get depressed
sales after you've sucked up the two and
a half percent of the laws by something
you anyway
so effectively the dominance of the
previous idea
starts to explain the reason for the
suppression of novelty in the chasm
now one of the examples i normally give
on this is to look at
ibm's total dominance of computing
from really the 70s through the 80s into
the 90s
and the reason ibm was able to do that
is
that they repurposed if you remember
that word exception
from the first of these lectures what
they did is they were
had worldwide confidence in punch cards
from various manufacturing machine
control devices
so they repurposed that competence to
create the first
ever programs which were all card based
for those of us who are old enough to
remember it yeah
if you learn to program on punch cards
you have real programming discipline
[Music]
um you also learn to carry things
carefully there's a few lessons you get
from punch cards
so basically because they already knew
how to do punch cards and they'd been
through all the grief
they were highly competent in that that
gave them first mover advantage and then
they controlled the ait industry
i mean they had the worst hardware and
the worst software
um things like you know the deca alpha
were infinitely better when the ibm pc
when they came out and the vax clusters
took it out performing as400 sorry i'm
sure my age now
um but basically people didn't buy the
best thing they bought the safest thing
that's actually quite important to
remember so as you move into mature
markets
people want to buy what other people
have bought there was a phrase then
nobody gets
fired for buying ibm so
buy something novel and different and it
goes wrong it will all be your fault
buy ibm and it goes wrong it won't be
your fault because everybody else made
the same mistake mckinsey's are playing
off this hugely at the moment in the
consultancy market
um it's kind of like there are
infinitely certainly in an agile
virtually any agile consultancy
is a lot better than mckinsey's in doing
the job but you're not going to get
fired if you hire mckenzie's because of
their reputation
and remember that this is a conservative
buying pattern
now because of that so ibm gets first
mover advantage it pulls out to the
chasm it dominates that early adopter
phase
which means it controls the late adopter
markets which is where all the
revenue is yeah um i'm going to tell you
something depressing about politics on
this at the end because it applies there
as well but let's keep the commercial
for the moment
now the trouble is that once something
reaches its late majority phase it's
starting to become a commodity
and as it starts to become a commodity
other players can produce things quicker
and cheaper
but the trouble is if you're the apex
predator the top of the supply chain you
don't see it because your price is
protected for a very long time
so the shock when it hits you is almost
catastrophic
you might remember ibm at that time was
the largest ever corporate loss in world
history
and it's been far exceeded since but it
was kind of like a major first
so basically because they're a commodity
they don't see
the price drops come in they start they
don't realize what's going to happen
and we got a completely new apex
protector in the iit industry a little
software company called microsoft
um which had actually been paid by ibm
to develop an operating system which
they quasi stole from somebody else
anyway
and ipm didn't think software was
significant it was all about hardware
um so they let bill have the ip rights
to it
and lo and behold you've got an apex
predator
now this apex predator concept is key
because the entire ecosystem
organizes around it there's a video it's
worth looking at if you type trophic
cascade wolves in yellowstone into
google
you'll find a wonderland wonderful
little video which shows what happened
when they reintroduce wolves into
yellowstone
because they were the apex predator with
wolves
near deer were curled deered in
riverbanks because they were afraid of
wolves
um water run clear
so basically the apex predator survives
no matter
how incompetent they are because the
ecosystem self organizes around them
and of course when the ecosystem is
destroyed the apex predator can no
longer survive so a new one comes
through when the meteor wipes out the
dinosaurs
you know if you had the guess on the
successor you go for the crocodile or
the shark you wouldn't go
for the first mammal but actually
something very small and very
energy efficient is more likely to come
through the stage
so that's the the apex predator concept
and once they're established you get a
trophic cascade and the rest of the
ecosystem organizes around them
so again they survive even if they're
incompetent
yeah until the ecosystem itself is
disrupted
so the hardware to software shift was a
massive ecosystem disruption triggered
by commodification
and then the same thing happens again so
microsoft dominate the space they can
command whatever money they want
everybody
has to buy windows despite the fact it's
appalling software sorry
and a macbook um
yeah it's and don't talk about words and
powerpoint for god's sake right
um so but everybody buys it because it's
a safe purchase but it becomes a
commodity you start to get free software
you start to get the open source
movement
and microsoft doesn't realize that until
it's too late
i mean it's reinventing itself because a
completely different company at the
moment
just like ibm reinvented itself as a
services company not a hardware company
yeah so kind of like if you've got cash
you can do that a lot of companies go
under
now the entire european computer
industry went under by the way
at the same time as ibm's just
disappeared
because it was working in a commodity
market and of course when microsoft
realized that they suddenly discovered
that apple have overtaken them
because apple realized that the ecobuild
system was about integrated hardware and
software people weren't concerned about
the hardware or the software they were
concerned about having something
beautiful which did something they
didn't know they wanted until they had
it
and then they couldn't do without it
that was apple's initial success
and we'll go through this cycle again um
i think this one will be longer because
apple are taking an ecosystem route
rather than rather than a product route
yeah so they may be able to stay in it
longer but this is a natural cycle
um you will also see the cycle in
politics
so if you go back some what
neoliberalism did
was it homogenized politics
yeah it actually meant both republicans
and democrats or labour and conservative
were all competed in from the center
ground they all accepted neo-liberalism
so there was no difference
between the major political parties or
people didn't see a difference
again that's the commodification phase
that means the energy cost
of a completely new predator coming into
the ecosystem goes radically down
so when you lose strategic diversity and
you get homogenization
something new can come in as trump did
or as the far-right and the conservative
party did in the uk
at very low energy cost because the
system is ready for that type of radical
disruption
so this this framework has a wider
purpose um
now if we don't look at it in more
detail you actually got this
key period if i can get this to advance
which i currently can't
okay you get this period here
where basically if you're the dominant
predator at the moment
you're now hitting this particular point
yeah
this particular point here which i call
the example point
um that's where you should realize that
you're reaching the peak
of your overall market dominance you're
starting to see novel competitors
you're not having a problem competing
with them you can wipe them out but
there's an increasing number of them
and some of them are starting to gain
traction that's where you need to make a
radical shift in your business
if you don't do it you reach this point
um which is called competence-induced
failure
this is the point and this goes back to
clayton christiansen's
work and i did some work with clayton
christians in one
project product and we talked a lot
about this then
um because this puts context on what he
says as christian pointed out
companies don't fail because they're
incompetent
they fail because they're too competent
at the old paradigm
so people can't see that actually the
old power of them doesn't work anymore
yeah you can see that for example in
hillary
clinton's campaign in the last american
presidential election i'll give you lots
of other examples
yeah the old frameworks aren't working
anymore
um but they're the dominant way of
thinking so you effectively have this
very narrow gap here
where you can make an adjustment now
there is important things which come out
of this
um the first is if you actually look at
nearly all
industries all political systems or
social systems seem to go through this
cycle
the work i'm building into this at the
moment is not just to look
at the apex predator but also to look at
keystone species things like beavers
and i'd argue that in i.t for a long
time intel went down a keystone species
model
it may have been the apex in microchips
but in overall computing
its chips were used by everybody it was
kind of like the supplier of choice
apple went in and out and so on
so a keystone species is something which
sustains the ecosystem but doesn't
dominate it
an apex predator dominates the system
and we can go
and add some more metaphors in this as
we go
but the principle of this framework and
it's to my mind is up there with
canaveral as a sense making framework
although it's about five to six years
behind in development
it's basically says that in different
contexts different things are possible
so if you're in if you come out of that
early adopter phase
and that ends at the competence induced
failure point that's the 30 and a half
percent
if you're not in total if you're not
actually dominating the market at that
point somebody else
is and you'll lose the rest of the
business
now at that point your strategy and i'm
sorry to carry on with these african
metaphors is a hyena strategy
you have to feed off the scraps of the
dominant predator
so you have to become for example a
microsoft certified supplier
or if you're in agile at the moment and
by the way agile is way past the stage
in heavy commodification at the moment
you end up having to be a safe certified
consultant which is to my mind a form of
controlled and certified insanity but
that's another matter
right basically you've got an apex
predator you have to serve the apex
predator because you can't compete with
it
there's very little room for competition
but when the apex predator starts to
become highly commodified and you can
see this by the way
with design thinking as well as with
agile at the moment
yeah they're both going through heavy
commodification phrases
that's when you introduce something new
and if you've got any sense you
introduce something new by this
exceptive term by taking something
you're competent at
and applying it to something completely
novel
i'm going to talk a bit next week about
how you can manage for serendipity which
is another way of describing that
so context is everything if you're in
the growth phase
and you can look at this in terms of
organizational change
so if your company's got a new ceo and a
new h director and they've fallen in
love with some consultants over the
model you're not going to be able to
shake it
until it starts to fail or until it
becomes so commodified and commonplace
it no longer
adds value there's no point in fighting
it then you have to wait
your moment you have to wait for the
commodification point to introduce
something new
all right now again this is important
because if you look at most of the post
prototype strategy approaches which come
out of systems thinking and cybernetics
they assume the strategy is not context
specific
they have the same models and the same
templates that you apply wherever you
are
what apex predator says very like
kinevin yeah and by the way i can map
this to kineman
you know i've got a chaotic point i've
got a complex point i've got an ordered
point
what apex predator says is first of all
what context you're in
that tells you what's possible yeah and
it tells you where the energy gradients
are coming back to what i said in the
first lecture you need to go where you
have the lowest
energy gradient the easiest form of
action so that in a
high level yeah um
is apex predator theory now
linked to this and this comes into
the work we did on counter terrorism so
there were two
things i was tasked to do when i took
this contract on and this was years
back it was before 9 11. so i got
summoned down to washington and met a
really nice old man and we had a great
conversation
and after i decided that i really liked
him i saw a picture of him with ronald
reagan and discovered i was talking with
admiral john poindexter
you might remember with reagan's nsa at
the time with the iran-contra affair but
i'm sorry i will defend him he's still a
friend
um and i ended up working for him on
darpa projects for about a decade
and we had a series of tasks one was the
weak signal detection task
so how do you identify an outlier
remember the 17
from the first lecture how do i identify
people who've seen a gorilla but nobody
is listening to
so that was kind of like task number one
um
task number two and i'll never forget
when he said this he said when he was
nsa
when he asked for advice people competed
not to tell him the truth but to have
their advice accepted
the more senior you are in government or
industry the more people compete to tell
you what you want to hear
and because that's how they survive
and what he wanted was disintermediation
a system by which he could look at the
entire landscape and go direct to raw
intelligence reports
without any mediation or interpretation
and that i'm going to talk a bit about
the next week as well
and the third thing um he was looking at
and this is something we can have his
discussion like completely next week
he said how and he didn't phrase it like
this but max pastor and i were with him
and
i remember we both said you want us to
reverse ashby's law then indeed
now remember ashby's law from the early
age of information science
says that only variety can match variety
so you get increasing levels of data
stimulation you have to increasingly
pump up the energy level of your
response and you can't like go up this
line
to the point where you end up with
aircraft security in the days when we
used to fly around the world right
only a year ago now i'm going to give it
um
where they actually the cost of
preventing failure is out of all
proportion to the benefit
and that's what's called asymmetric
warfare what the terrorist is doing is
making your cost of defending against
them so high that you will concede
now the steph max and i did with john
was to actually look at how do you
reverse ashby's law
by using human sensor networks so how
the governments
become asymmetric powers not symmetric
pose
and that actually feeds into new forms
of democracy so i'll probably pick up
that next week
um but part of that is this apex theory
is it basically says in different
contexts the energy gradient of change
is very
low in other contexts the energy
gradient of change is high
if you're not aware of it then you'll be
destroyed and we saw that with
neoliberal economics
yeah um we've seen it with ibm we've
seen it with microsoft we will see it
with apple
um we've seen it we're seeing it at the
moment with design thinking
we're definitely seeing it with agile
this is kind of like a standard cycle
if you're aware of it you can hit the
renewal button before it's too late
because you may notice under confidence
induced failure that line just goes on
down
yeah and you actually disappear now key
to all of those three poindexter
questions which i raised and this is
where i'm going to introduce something
and then
really go into this next week
is this right now
i extracted the top picture from trisha
wang
um who blogs on this you can find the
reference yeah
um i'm paranoid about acknowledging
sources i get really upset when some
people
don't and she produced the top model
which compared big data with thick data
um she's an ethnographer this is
becoming a very fashionable thing for
people with an ethnographic
training so she said big data
yeah has very large volume data sets
and it gains an insight from that
through algorithmic interpretation
but the depth of the insight she said is
shallow
she then contrasts that with an
ethnographer who is dealing with low
volumes of the data but high volumes of
meaning
and that she called thick data right and
she basically says you need thick data
to complement big data
now i remember looking at this and
saying well there's a lot of white space
on that
um big data actually increases meaning
as you get more and more
data so she's got that wrong it's not a
column yeah it will actually as you get
huge volumes
yeah you start to actually get to higher
levels of meaning
but thick data doesn't scale so the work
we focused on which i'll go through next
week and this is called sensemaker which
is a primarily sense making tool
is and this links in with the human
sensor networks
is by allowing people to self-interpret
their own experience on a continuous
basis
into a quantitative framework you can
get the benefits of scale
with the richness of human
interpretation
yeah now i'm going to just spend a
couple more minutes on that because i
want this one to hang around in your
minds for a bit
i'm ready for next week so what we're
seeking to do
is increase the human interpretation
within the system
now there are also defensive reasons for
that so
at the moment the internet particularly
social media
is an unbuffered feedback loop
right so if you look at what happens
particularly in the current political
climate
you've got whole bot farms yeah you've
got individual malicious actors
the system has no buffering in it and
any amber for
the feedback loop always leads to
perverse outcomes
you might remember computer training
algorithms um
computer trading algorithms which almost
destroyed the economy
you know because they went into an into
a into an unbuffered feedback loop
yeah there's no controls so what we're
doing
is to use citizens including school
children
activists ordinary citizens nurses
doctors people in their day-to-day roles
um effectively as self-ethnographers to
their own
day-to-day experiences and shift in the
power of interpretation from the expert
in the algorithm to the individual
responsible for the data
but in a quantitative way and i'll say
i'll talk about how we do this
next week but the principle is to get
very rich data and in real time to be
able to stimulate that network to give
feedback
for distributed decision support now
that is going to be the big
theme of next week is how do you
distribute
decision support because you need
cognitively
culturally educationally diverse groups
otherwise you'll miss 17 and it's
also linked in with the issue of power
because at the moment
um if you look at the way democracy
doesn't work
yeah it's the tyranny of the person with
the most money to create the most
algorithms to run the most adverts
people's ordinary wishes don't show
it through show through and you see this
also in consumer spending and everything
else
so this ability to understand
not just raw content but also how people
interpret that content becomes key all
right so that's
and i remember i was thinking about
trump when i wrote the blog post so i
wrote the blog post is called big thick
and rich
right so you can take it from there but
the
idea is all three types of data are
important but the rich data is probably
the most important because it's the most
responsive to change
and it's important to remember that
algorithms are entirely based on
training data sets
they cope with novelty less well in
humans
and ethnographers are entirely based on
which particular school they were
trained in
so neither is is free of three of
significant bias yeah you never get rid
of bias overall but you should try and
reduce significant bias
now what that is also going to give us
is a means of
triggering an alert when we reach an
accepted moment
and i'm trading next week now that's
called an anticipatory trigger
because human beings are very good at
noticing an anomaly
if you tell them there is anomaly that
they're hopeless if you don't
so you may remember as kids all right
you've got these pictures of
line drawings of a park and the question
would be how many kitchen utensils are
hidden in the park
and because you knew there was something
hidden in the park you could see them
and spot them but if you weren't told
you would never see them so
anticipatory triggers are designed to
bring human beings to pay attention
to weak signals before they become
dominant circles
so they can recognize those shifts
within the apex curves
or you know more simple things like
competitive or
industrial threat or whatever so that's
high level
yeah and as i say this framework sort of
sits alongside kinevin
and the stuff i'm introducing now on big
thick on the rich data
is kind of like the third um leg of the
stool
you know can navin is a primary
sense-making framework
apex predator theory as a means of
determining where you are
and the whole issue of distributed
narrative sense making
um as a new method of research insight
and decision support
so those are the three things i'll cover
over the time
and i've taken my 40 minutes i think yes
i have so
open to questions thanks dave that was
great
um personally i'm really excited for
next week i was
excited about this topic from day one so
i'm really looking forward to next week
um so we have a couple questions
maybe i'll give someone a chance to ask
before i do um
so first we have i'm not sure if i'm
pronouncing this correctly but
titia ttf you have a question you'd like
to ask
do you uh yes yes it's here so
you pronounce it all right so my
question is um on these two curves
between this acceptive point and
competitive competence induced failure
is that also
the point where you see companies
annexing or buying
that novel player
yeah i think and that's one strategy but
it only works for so long
and that's if they see it um you
generally find they often buy too late i
mean it's been quite interesting and
agile the big six have been buying up
agile companies
at ridiculous p e ratios they're
actually not buying the company they're
buying the brand
and those prices are longer on offer so
people have got more sophisticated about
recovery strategies
yeah if you've got a lot of cash
um but generally towards the right hand
side of that yellow space people start
to realize
it's not working and they panic the
sooner you realize you're at that moment
the less panic you have to do
um okay and next we have tony
tony of question you like to ask
well it really wasn't a question
necessarily
but it was a the the comment was uh the
work that you did with uh dave's
uh excuse me went up uh with uh
poindexter about disintermediation of
of raw data that's sort of what got us
into the iraq war
because cheney the vice president at the
time loved to look at the raw
intelligence reports and and draw his
own conclusions which may or may not
have been
informed by any kind of context or the
context that he wanted to read into them
that was my only comment yeah i mean
and i was around at that time all right
um spent all my time in dc the fact is
that one agent can't read all the
reports that's the danger
so what actually happened is you read
the ones which match what you want to
hear
so poindexter could have done that
anytime what he wanted is something
which visualized
all of the available intelligence so he
could see patterns
and that would focus him on reading
things he needed to read and that's a
radical difference
yeah and that was what we did
i did have an entertaining time in the
pentagon by quoting roman
doctrine on military doctrine on
invading syria
um the romans had it worked out they
said if you have a rebellion in
in the parthians all right which is the
same area
um because they were fighting iraq then
as well you know move in with
overwhelming flaws and wait outside the
capital city
and let the factions fight each out each
it out and then move in and support the
winning faction
if you move in and conquer the city all
the factions will unite against you and
you won't achieve your results and i
remember saying that and i still stand
by that as advice
that's sort of like when the english
show up you're welch
yeah and i mean the english i mean they
practiced on the welsh
every time they invaded us they had more
welsh troops fighting for them than
english troops
and that's how they conquered india they
did it by exploiting local differences
in the people they were conquering it
was and it was a very successful
strategy
yet you guys wanted to make everybody
american that never works
okay great um i have a question with a
couple plus ones
um it was an anonymous question
i will ask it for the person um if the
ecosystem
shifts towards an experienced economy
what do the apex predator and keystone
species look like
did you understand the question i think
that's interesting
i mean it's part of the problem we
addressed in the early days of knowledge
management
where companies were starting to hire in
people
so the idea then was you no longer have
lifetime employment
you're expected to move on every two to
three years
um and then it was held this would be a
benefit to you the reality it meant
that you just rented your knowledge you
only
contributed what you really needed to
contribute
and for me a lot of the experienced
economy is no different from the get a
gig economy
because the danger is you have to
actually i mean
it's a it's it's the issue about what
people will do for you are you paying
them to
do something yeah which you know you
want
or are they part of your inner ecosystem
and they're part of generating novelty
and new ideas you didn't know you needed
and also the nature of experience is
also critical to understand
so for example there's a whole body of
human knowledge
um which takes two to three years
minimum to acquire
you can't just learn it yeah it's it's
knowledge in your fingertips or
heuristics
so i think there's a lot been talked
about here and people aren't going back
and remember
some of the similar mistakes i think the
real thing
on the economy is is not using
experience
as mediation instead of money or skills
or whatever
the real issue and the one thing i'm
interested in the moment is
is how gifting works because i
did a lot of work on this in aboriginal
communities in australia back in the 70s
uh gifting in indigenous communities is
an entry fee it's not
an exchange so if you gift your part
to the community the community looks
after you if you don't gift you're
excluded
and the gift isn't as i say an equal
exchange
now there's absolutely no reason why we
shouldn't give free at the point of
entry health care education and social
services everywhere in the world
it's just we choose not to we ration it
with money
indigenous communities don't ration
things with with a means of exchange
they have a gifting culture
and to me i think that's one of the
areas we've got to start to look at
right in terms of the next generation
economy
and i think covered is driving that
faster because the
breakdown in traditional economic
discipline the increasing dependency of
local communities on support
we're starting to see some of those
changes i mean neoliberalism
was a bad idea in the first place and
thank god he's dead but i really don't
want it to be replaced with fascism
which still seems like the most likely
alternative at the moment
so i think we need to start to look at
look at these sort of different things
and we also need to think about the
competence because
i mean one of the sentence making
frameworks i created i've only gone
through a few of them
in in four or four lectures all right
it's called ashen
which starts it stands for artifact
skills heuristics experience and natural
talent
and it's a mechanism for knowledge
mapping so when somebody makes a
decision
you say you cluster those decisions and
you say when you made that decision what
artifacts did you use
you know artifacts comes from artists in
fact though
something man-made yeah what skills were
necessary and a skill is something you
can train somebody to do and know
whether they've got
it or not yeah what heuristics are
present
because heuristics are a key method by
which experts
make decisions what experience is
necessary and what
natural talent is there yeah and what we
basically argue with that is all five of
those things come into play in different
balances in different contexts
so the danger is you start to say we're
not in this economy we're not in economy
x we're in economy why
yeah you know it's like bpr we're no
longer vertically focused for
horizontally focused you these constant
switches
from one thing to another and don't
realize that all
all things have validity within
different contexts within different
boundaries
yeah so it's this desire to always
create the new thing and
you see it a lot now i get really angry
with it on social media don't get angry
i just get irritated and that's
always dangerous right yeah somebody
puts up two columns and on the left are
terrible evil things and on the right to
terrible
you know things that i'm selling which
by definition are not evil
and i always look at them and i want to
draw you know kind of like well actually
most of the stuff on the left
there's nothing wrong with it in some
contexts you know
and a lot of the stuff on the right
would be a bad idea so
we need to get much more sophisticated
about the way we talk about this
and we also need to create economies
which are not dependent on skills or
experience
if you want to have a civilization
you've got to have jobs for people
who don't have skills and experience
yeah and then people just start thinking
about that i mean it's quite
i mean i don't know where it's still the
case i always used to like driving from
um
washington state down to portland
um because i didn't have to fill up the
gas anymore
because you're not allowed to get out
the car and fill out the gas they do it
for you so they've got effectively an
employment
tax you know there's people who have to
be employed to fill up your tank
right and and i'm not saying that should
be universal but they're not just
letting in automation
can replace all the jobs for people
because then you get a terrible
underclass and you don't have to read
much science fiction you know the
consequences of that density
but i think that's a really good segue
into the
other question dave are you familiar
with the game
b space kmb
now i'm not a game player and i think it
all it all got too difficult after space
invaders to be honest
you know okay okay um
maybe maybe i'll i'll see so i will make
a general comment
though i mean we've seen this in a lot
of our work
and we've seen it in some of the
military game players
yeah most games involve understanding
the rules
and life isn't like that
so you need to be very careful on it i
mean we we have a game system we use
called answer simulation which is set up
so that people can't succeed
run by human games masters and the rules
are changed by the games masters
as they go through to make sure people
for help
but you know it's interesting because
when you were talking about the
experience economy
well i interpreted a completely
different way and i'm not sure how the
person who asked the question and uh
meant it when i heard experience economy
i heard
um as opposed to things like
um i can buy this mug i can buy an
experience of like watching
a netflix show or experience of going to
disney world or something like that
experience having to be
something that's immaterial something
that's um attracting
okay now right we call that the service
economy
or maybe using different language there
um you still have to have something
which you're producing
yeah there has to be some heart on the
economy the huge weakness of the british
economy a moment is we're entirely
reliant on financial services and we're
about to lose them
yeah we've got no primary manufacturing
but i mean the points still stand right
there is that there is there is not one
right way of doing things there are
multiple
rise ways of doing things in different
contexts
okay uh andy you have the question
hi i wanted to ask about the
domains let me pull back and see
so if the competencies change
as valued by society with time
i want to know if there's some sub
competencies
that we can define that will change
the apex predator curve either make it
deeper
shift it to the left or right so let me
give an example so
u.s healthcare delivery used to the
competency used to be
uh let's say relationship or
quality and now it's convenience um
so a cultural change has happened is
there a way to
um generalize that to other domains
i think it's an important point i mean i
i'm meeting up with three doctors i go
walking with tomorrow i've been on my
own this week but now i'm with them for
the weekend
and jess's advice never go walking with
three doctors if anything goes wrong
with you they'll spend all their time
arguing about it while you die or
all right um one doctor is a good idea
but one things they all say is they
don't want to be operated on by anybody
under 50.
because what happened to medical
training in the uk
at that equivalent point is it went from
people
effectively being trained as teams with
people they know where people covered
for your mistakes and looked after you
and you gradually gained experience
into people having designated
qualifications being allocated to teams
automatically
they were treated as a commodity yeah
rather than as people
so that's leading to a breakdown in the
healthcare sector in the us and the uk
right which relates to the care issue
now you've got various ways that that
can go one is we could go to an entirely
faith-healing alternative and you can
see some of that you know why didn't you
swallow some bleach
and you won't get covered and that sort
of thing is growing
um you could start to reintroduce
primary care with people who are based
in communities and want to work with
communities but that itself is difficult
we're doing work at the moment on
conflict in maternity services
where the professionals would you know
ideally want all women put into hospital
at six months and put
into a bed and you know basically
managed to produce the perfect baby
and can't understand why women don't
like this idea and want to stay within
the communities and get care at the
local level
yeah and that sort of modification
and that failure to appreciate it yeah
is part of the problem right so i think
some of the strategies we've got to do
is we've got to create
and this comes into complexity theory um
you can't tackle the dominant attractor
if you've got a dominant negative
attractor if you attack it directly
you'll make it worse that's the mistake
liberals are making him criticizing
trump
now you you don't tackle those things
directly you tackle it by making
alternative attractors stronger so they
take energy away from the negative
attractor
so i think the secret to making the
change is
the sort of small parallel experiments
we talked about on kinevin
but also some of the apparatic
techniques um
and i only went into those briefly but
the whole point about apparatic
techniques is
is to create irresolvable paradoxes or
contradictions so people are forced to
act and think differently
yeah i you can't flip into the norm but
i think you've raised a really important
point and we've got to try and do more
of it
and the other thing i think is and this
partly comes actually into the
experience economy per your question
going back to that a bit um
the more you increase the
personalization of a product the less
it's a commodity
yeah and and that's important to realize
and it's been kind of we've been going
through hell lately on legal fronts and
god knows what else and one things which
i've learned from that is loyalty
matters
um and it's amazing how loyal people are
if you've treated them
with respect and you've actually done
things and all that sort of thing and i
think that the loyalty element
and that there's community limitations
on this
the part of the problem we've got with
politics is we're too far removed from
the people we elect
right um democracy actually evolved for
a system where you knew who your
representative was to parliament or the
congress it didn't resolve for a system
where
you were just one of 150 or 200 000 and
you had no idea who you were voting for
and i'm actually blogging about this at
the moment right
um so i think one of the key things
we've got to do and this
generally i'm starting a series of blogs
on the subject of intimacy
um which is not me getting to be a dirty
old man or anything like that i hasten
to add but it's saying you need to
increase
intimacy within service position with
commodities because actually that's how
you create differentiation and loyalty
is there a way to scale loyalty
yeah i think there is but i think you
scale it by nodal networks i mean we
valdez krebs and i are doing an
exploratory in the new year
if you know voldiscrabs like he's the
best person i know in the world on
network analysis
so one of the things we're going to be
exploring at that is what type of
nodal networks um create the highest
level of rapid promulgation of
emittive behavior which is beneficial
yeah i mean the key thing you've got to
realize is that behavior evolves it
can't be designed
this is a big mistake of behavioral
economists
you know that they're thinking they can
design behavior and they had they had a
hawthorn effect at the start because it
was novel to get a letter saying that
your
neighbor had paid their tax and you
hadn't right
um but it's no longer novel so it's past
the hawthorne stage
and it's manipulative
uh dave do you have a couple minutes
maybe 10-15 minutes extra
yeah sure okay perfect thank you for
humoring us
again and again um i believe on the
point of medical care i
believe um dan dan you got a question a
follow-up question for that
uh point he just made
john feldman um what was i'm sorry what
was the
question
oh i'm sorry i can't hear you
you you asked about the bert's uh
berkshire method uh i think you were
talking about dave i think you were
talking about
um uh intimacy
and primary care spreading out primary
care and i was wondering if the
i know you're not a fan of the
reinventing organization's book as i'm
not
uh i'm not either but uh the cons
the the idea that that the bert's org
organization
where that was highlighted in that book
where
the uh i guess the members of this
organization
meet the patients directly and they're
kind of self-managed or self-organized
and i was wondering if you had any
comments on that
i think it suffers from all the cases in
that book that he only picks the parts
of the cases which
actually support his religious beliefs
and that that's the problem with
everything in the crocs yeah he's got an
ideology and he's highly selective in
what he presents
um and that's been around for some time
and hasn't scaled
yeah and i think the trouble is you can
lose these things very quickly they
build over years
um so the whole sort of concept of the
primary care the doctor
lived in the neighborhood whose father
was your doctor before you or his mother
was your doctor before you and you
everybody knew the family
the total depersonalization of health
care is is now a problem
right and it's not going to be solved by
some behavioral training and some
inspired leadership is going to be have
to be solved by far more systematic
change
yeah in the way we do things
and you know part of that i think
i speak at the moment having you know
i'm 66 and i'm walking 30 miles a day
and climbing 4000 feet a day
and meeting people in their 40s
struggling to get up 200 meters to a
popular tourist site
and we're not doing enough on on health
yeah we're doing too much on the sort of
you know diagnosed cure type cycle yeah
so we're not creating resilience in the
population
and again i think we've got to look at
ways of scaling that
and i think it's got to be something
which what
and i think it's a key principle for
complexity when it emerges we'll
recognize it but we can't design it up
front
and the problem with all of the crocs
types books and there's many
is they're trying to design utopia
and that never works yeah what you have
to do is to change the constraints and
see what works and then amplify the
things which do and dampen the things
which don't
thank you actually
um i'll give you an
i'm just going to tell another story so
ask another question go for it no no
please
please go ahead please uh it was an
example
i had to give a lecture to um a thing
called spring summing down
which is every year all of the um
the heads of you know the civil service
heads and all the heads of british
industry get together for three days off
site
so it's chatham house rules yeah and it
was rather amusing because i got invited
to speak and i got
the best slot which is the after dinner
slot because then you get to have a meal
with the guys and stay around and get
drunk with them right
which is a lot better than just having a
20-minute presentation during the day
and i still remember i told the ibm
general manager for
britain i've been invited and i got this
vicious email back saying why have you
usurped an invitation intended for
somebody more senior than you
and which point yeah the cabinet office
had to explain i've been invited despite
the fact i worked for ibm not because i
had
and then they sent me a slide set and
wanted to rehearse me and what they
wanted me to say and they had to have
another conversation with the cabinet
office
either way i got there and i was doing a
basic complexity canadian type
thing um because we used extensively on
well a whole bunch of stuff on foreign
policy and things like that
so i was presenting it um and just
before i started
the permanent secretary for health ran
up to me
and said you can't use the matron
example
and i said why can't i use the matron
example and he said because
you know i'll come back to that in a
minute right and the matron example was
very simple i use it a lot in complexity
so it used to be and it was all girls in
those days young girls left school
became a nurse lived in a nursing
hospital
you know got their qualifications
gradually came up the rank and
throughout this period they were
terrified of this figure called the
matron
it was the most senior nurse and then
one day they discovered they were the
matron
and the matron picked up on all the
pieces the other parts of the system
didn't deal with
and if you were a junior adopter
technically you could tell the nature
what to do but god help you if you tried
you know it was like the young
lieutenant trying to say something to a
staff
sergeant it was the same sort of result
um now it's interesting because when
they allowed men to become nurses it's
quite interesting now the dominant
number of nurse managers are male
even though the number of nurses are
female then that should tell us
something
but what also happened is they got rid
of matrons
because they said they were super
surplus level of management nobody could
see what they did
now the reality is they held the system
together like hassan you know like the
regimental sergeant major the staff
sergeant all these sort of people did
they didn't get rid of them in northern
ireland which was interesting
yeah um and the reason they did include
them in northern ireland is they were
holding the system together because you
had young nurses dealing with their
boyfriend from school coming in with his
knees shut off
as a punishment killing all right so i
mean that this
uh read the story of mar today it's
written by one of the nurses there which
is a good friend of
mine it's brilliant you know what they
had to put it up within belfast
so they didn't get rid of it then so i
always use as an example of an evolved
role that you get rid of your peril
and say the the guy in charge of house
said you can't use the example and i
said well you know
i've been told to do it by defendants
because they've kept their sergeants and
you got rid of their matrons and i'm
more scared of defense than i am of you
so i'm going to use it anyway and i
never get he said well you can't use it
because we're bringing back
matrons i said oh great you've got a
30-year process have you he said oh no
we've got a two-week training course
and we're giving them a career to become
doctors
and i use the example he just haven't
understood it um
stable stabilizing elements of social
systems take decades to evolve
they can't just be designed and put in
place instantly
and that's something we've got to start
to understand in politics and everything
else
yeah that's a real challenge for
evaluating
new programs or programs that's yeah
there's a desire for a quick hit i mean
that's why lacrosse book sells because
it sounds wonderful and everybody knows
they won't have to do it
that's perfect for most executives buy a
program which you know is full of
platitude say you're gonna do it and
just carry on as normal
most of agiles like that
so uh maybe we have time for a couple
more two more questions
uh anja and always has a lot of very
good questions so angela would you ask
one of your questions
uh we can't hear you for some reason i
can't hear you
can you hear me now yeah okay
um dave i noticed you use a fair number
of
natural analogies um to biology
to nature and i'm curious
do you think they're just analogies or
is there a chance
um it's something more
it's actually i think it's something
more but i don't want to get
new age fluffy bunny about this right um
but we i mean part of the problem is
northern europe
and northern america has got
thoroughly into cartesian dualism the
belief that the mind is separate from
the body
and part of the problem we got with what
i call the adoption of faux buddhism
in the states is it furthers that
distinction it claims not to but it
actually furthers it
yeah and the reality is that
consciousness is
distributed function of the body
and the brain and its social connections
andy clark's work on this has shown that
narrative
structures in society are part of our
extended consciousness
um so we are physical creatures
i mean and you know this whole concept
of this singularity and if you believe
in the singularity your brain is
probably ossified to the point where for
you it may be possible
yeah human consciousness is not like
that
it's much more distributed we know that
for example
pheromone traces have a significant
pickup in humans in determining trust
which is a problem with virtual
communication so we are physical
creatures in a physical world
um and the distinction the separation of
us from that physical world is behind
things like global warming all sorts of
other things
yeah i spend a lot of my time working
with indigenous communities they don't
make that separation
now you can't adopt their practices
intact but you can learn from that
yeah and that's where i was coming onto
the concept of gifting
the other thing it's worth reading and i
know in a catholic school i shouldn't be
doing this but the pope's encyclical on
the environment called la doty say
should be read because he's a chemist
and we're actually doing some work on
this at the moment
and if you look at a lot of modern
religious practice it's actually about
reintegrating us with the physical world
yeah as that sort of sense of something
other
uh the technical term for this is
numinous which we're running projects on
at the moment
the sense that there's something more
than you so i think that's one aspect of
it
the other is the chemicals play far more
part in our decision-making than we like
to think
so the ecological metaphors do come
across as
physical descriptions not as metaphors
they're not deterministic though that's
the difference they're deterministic in
termites nests
but they're not deterministic in humans
they're dispositional
very interesting so maybe we'll have
time for one more question
um sorry thief i took so long to ask you
a question deep are you still here
i want to ask you yes okay sorry
uh well it's tough to keep up with
father jargon and all the different
models
but the question sort of keyed in when
you described
asset matter asymmetric warfare how you
the
terrorists just wear down the defenses
if you could you
use that same analogy to sort of say how
the inframage
information age and technology 24 7
news social media has sort of flooded
the masses with too much information to
process yeah so they're
you can't make the decisions so maybe
whoever the apex predators are sort of
taking advantage of this landscape of
just
the masses just can't navigate this sort
of
confusing flooded mess and
if i gave a lecture on that in dc just
before last november when i was over
yeah
but what what you do the whole point is
if you flood people with too much
information they start to delegate
decision making
and the minute people delegate decision
making the people
you know they'll just go i mean the way
i said it once which i still stand by
is everybody used to trust experts from
the 40s onwards
and if you look at the news then you
have consideration it's once per day
everybody watches it
you get journalism now we've got
information saturation and people can't
cope so they're trying populists for a
change
so i think that's that's one point all
right the the sheer
volume of information creates an
asymmetric threat
actually to our survival as a species or
certainly as a humane species
and and that's critical right the other
thing sorry
i'm going to react a little bit to your
use of the word jargon writing quote
heidiger
and heidi famously said man thinks he's
the master of language but language is
the master of man
if you don't change people's language
you don't change the way they think
yes uh we have some really interesting
other questions but i think we should
close it up here for now um
just to give you a preview of some of
the things that people are thinking
about dave
um someone asked can you
talk more about your metaphysical views
and personally i've been interested in
your
in your religious views as well so maybe
sometime you can talk about that
um maybe i'll give you some a little bit
of time to talk about what you want to
a brief introduction for next week or
anything else you want to close off with
um okay i i wrote a blog recently where
i confess to being a pelagian i think
pelagianism is the heresy to adopt so i
recommend that
anything sin augustine opposed is to be
supportive because anybody who could
write the bloody city of god which i was
forced to read deserves to be punished
right
and but pelagian is called the british
heresy
it's the belief that you have free will
and there's no original sin and i think
that's where we need to be at the moment
all right okay thank you dave thanks
everyone i just want to
make some announcements about uh stowe
session that's coming up tonight
um the name of it is called god bless
the broken bones and it's with
william farah olo holo ferrariolo i hope
earpinos are correct
it's at 7 30 um
[Music]
tonight 7 30 tonight also if you're
enjoying the store
um i want to invite you to um if you
feel
called to give a gift to the store on
patreon and i just posted the link
in the chat um but yeah well
thank you dave and thank you everyone
for the amazing questions and
um i hope to see everyone back here
again i think
on well soon it's in the uh on the event
page so we'll see you back
next week okay perfect thank you
everyone
take it easy
hi thank you so